# Lorenzo Feruglio

PhD Candidate at Politecnico di Torino



# Education

- 2014–now **PhD Candidate**, Aerospace Engineering, Politecnico di Torino, Torino, Professor: Sabrina Corpino.
  - 2016 Visiting Student Researcher (JVSRP) at **Jet Propulsion Laboratory** (JPL) for Mission Autonomy Research (Section 332H Alessandra Babuscia)
  - 2015 Visiting Student Researcher (JVSRP) at **Jet Propulsion Laboratory** (JPL) for Mission Autonomy Research (Section 332H Kar-Ming Cheung)
  - 2014 Exchange student at **Massachussetts Institute of Technology** 'CubeSat for Space Exploration: a new paradigm for Planetary Science Missions' (EAPS Sara Seager)
- 2009–2012 **Aerospace Engineering**, *Politecnico di Torino*, Torino, *Master of Science*. Graduated with Honors
- 2006–2009 Aerospace Engineering, Politecnico di Torino, Torino, Bachelor's Degree.

# Summary

research Autonomous Space Systems, Artificial Intelligence

experience Six years and counting of hands-on experience with CubeSats Polito CubeSat Team Leader for C&DH, AOCS and GCS design

knowledge CubeSat design, Space Systems Engineering, Subsystems (AOCS, C&DH, COMSYS) Algorithm design, STK, Matlab/Simulink, Python, C/C++, ESA-DRAMA, ECSS

hands-on e-st@r CubeSat AIT (Hardware in the Loop simulations)

projects e-st@rII CubeSat from design phase to LEOP and Commissioning3-STAR CubeSat for GNSS Remote Sensing and Earth Imaging

# Experience

# PhD Student - Space Systems Engineering

2014-now Mission Autonomy, Politecnico di Torino, Torino.

Methodologies and Technologies to Improve Small Satellites Space Mission Autonomy Current field of research:

- Neural networks for image quality assessment and event detection
- Fuzzy logics and Neural Networks for failure detection of actuators
- Definition of case studies (Interplanetary CubeSats) in order to investigate on mission autonomyenhancing technologies
- o Genetic Algorithms to optimize Multi-Attribute Tradespace Exploration problems
- o Hardware-In-The-Loop testing of training algorithms for neural networks for asteroid recognition

### Space Systems Engineer

2013-2014 Assistant Researcher, Politecnico di Torino, Torino.

Capture and De-Orbiting Technologies.

Field of Research:

- o Development of a Simulator Technology to perform mission analyses and In-The-Loop simulations
- Research on GNC strategies for the latest phases of a rendez-vous and mating manoeuvre
- o Attitude Determination and Control Algorithms testing on specific hardware (ARM architecture)
- Code development and upgrading for ADCS and OBC subsystems (e-st@rII CubeSat)
- o e-st@r-II CubeSat Subsystem and System Functional Testing

#### 2012–2013 Operation Architecture Engineer, SES (contractor), Luxembourg.

Efficient Automation of Satellite Operations (EASO Project).

Detailed achievements:

- o Development, verification and validation of automated procedures for Satellite Operations
- Payload and Bus operation procedures for the SES Orbital fleet:
  - Dynamic Satellite Simulators (Orbital)
  - AOCS, TCR, TCS, EPS, CDH procedures development and subsystem analysis by means of DSS
  - Ground Control Station Software (SCORPIO)
- SPELL, Python, Eclipse

# 2009–2012 Polito CubeSat Team - Team member, Politecnico di Torino, Italy.

Member of the University CubeSat Team, developing and launching 1U+ CubeSats. Detailed achievements:

- Satellite (1U and 3U CubeSat) experience:
  - Systems Engineering methodologies
  - ADCS, C&DH Subsystem development and testing
  - CubeSat functional testing (test definition and execution)
  - ECSS standards for software development and testing
  - Real-time OS (Salvo, RTLinux)

### Skills

Analysis STK, Dynamic Satellite Simulation (AOCS, Failure Detection Systems), Space Debris Mitigation, Optimizations Techniques

Systems Eng ECSS, Multi-Attribute Tradespace Exploration, Satellite System Budgets, Mission Design and Functional Analysis

Programming Matlab/Simulink, Python, C/C++, Data Driven and Test Driven Development, SysML, UML, git

Embedded MPS430, ARM9, Raspberry-Pi, Satellite Hardware-In-The-Loop Testing

Miscellaneous MS Office, Visio, LaTex

OS UNIX (Ubuntu), RTLinux, Windows

Languages Italian (Mother language), English, basic French and German